Guide to the Malcolm Rutherford Thorpe Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Malcolm Rutherford Thorpe papers
1913-1952
MS 491
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
(9 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, reports, manuscripts and research material relating to Thorpe's geological surveys in Utah, to his work on vertebrate paleontology, to his directorship of the Peabody Museum of Natural History at Yale University, and to his work for the H. Emerson Tuttle Memorial Fund.
Thorpe, Malcolm Rutherford, 1891-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portion of papers gift of Malcolm Thrope in 1943.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence. II. Topical Files.
Biographical / Historical
MALCOLM RUTHERFORD THORPE (1891-1957)
Thorpe recieved his BA from Yale in 1913 and then took a Ph.D. in geology at Yale in 1916 and held a Yale College Fellowship during 1914-1915. In 1917 he surveyed positions for gun emplacements along the New England coast, under the U.S. Geologic Survey and the National Council of Defense, and the following year taught military geology to S.A.T.C. and R.O.T.C. students at Yale and military camps. He was a member of the University staff from 1919 until 1938, serving in the following capacities: preparator in vertebrate paleontology, 1919; assistant, 1919-1922; assistant curator, 1922-1927 (also fellow, 1922-1923); research associate, 1923-1938; curator 1927-1938; also curator of osteology, 1923-1938 (and taught osteological morphology, 1929-1938); acting director, Peabody Museum, 1927.
He served as a Commencement marshal from 1923 to 1928 and as chief Commencement marshal for the next ten years, was chief marshal for President Seymour's inauguration in 1937. He was chairman of the Emerson Tuttle Portrait Committee in 1945 and later (1946-1948) of the Emerson Tuttle Memorial Committee. He was an associate fellow of Davenport Colleg from 1933 onwards.
Thorpe carried out geological field work in various places, including South Dakota, Nebraska, Wyoming, Utah, Connecticut, Massachusetts, New Jersey, eastern and western Canada, and in England, Scotland, and France. He edited Organic Adaptation to Environment, published by the Yale University Press in 1924, and is the author of "The Osteology of Eporcodon Socialis Marsh" and "The Marycoidodantidae, An Extinct Group of Ruminant Mammals," both of which appeared in publications of Peabody Museum. He also contributed the sections on the Abajo Mountains to The San Juan Country, by Herbert E. Gregory. The U.S. Department of the Interior published a paper of his in 1939, and he has had some fifty other scientific articles published, as well as many reviews of scientific publications.
He belonged to the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, the Academy of National Sciences (Philadelphia), the Society of Vertebrate Paleontology, the Society of Mammalogists, the Geologic Society of America, the American Geographic Society, the Geochemical Society, and the American Association for the Advancement of Science, as well as to Phi Beta Kappa and Sigma Xi. He also belonged to the Graduates Club in New Haven.
Scope and Contents
The Malcolm R. Thorpe Papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts, notes, photographs, and miscellanea of Malcolm Rutherford Thorpe, a paleontologist and member of the Yale University staff from 1919-1938. The Thorpe Papers were a gift of Malcolm R. Thorpe in 1943, with subsequent additions. The papers are arranged in two series:
I. Correspondence, 1913-1952 II. Topical Files, 1923-1945
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE, 1913-1952, includes personal and professional correspondence with such correspondents as the U.S. Department of the Interior, Edmund Hovey Otis, and Ernest Howe.
SERIES II, TOPICAL FILES, 1923-1945, contains such material as a cataloge of Thorpe's personal library, descriptions of many specimens, his Ph.D. dissertation, and several manuscripts on topics of professional interest. Other materials include notes arranged under the topic "Memoirs of the Peabody Museum," chapters from Organic Adaption to Environment (1924), papers relating to the Emerson Tuttle Memorial Committee, and files for Yale University matters.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Geology -- Utah -- Surveys; Paleontology; Science; Vertebrates, Fossil; Utah -- Description and travel; Bateman, Alan M. (Alan Mara), 1889-1971; Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950; Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1849-1935; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; Doneghy, Mary Craddock; Eaton, George Francis, 1872-1949; Fields, Curtis P.; Gregory, Herbert E. (Herbert Ernest), 1869-1952; Hovey, Edmund Otis, 1862-1924; Howe, Ernest, 1875-1932; Lohmann, Carl A. (Carl Albert), 1887-; Merriman, John Campbell, 1869-1945; Palmer, Harold S. (Harold Schjoth), 1890-; Pierson, George Wilson, 1904-1993; Pilgrim, Guy Ellcock, 1875-; Schuchert, Charles, 1858-1942; Scott, William Berryman, 1858-1947; Stock, Chester, 1892-1950; Thorpe, Malcolm Rutherford, 1891-1957; Tittle, Walter, 1883-1966; Tuttle, H. E. (Henry Emerson), 1890-1946; Weber, Rudolph, d. 1933; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Woodward, Arthur Smith, 1864-1944; Peabody Museum of Natural History; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. H. Emerson Tuttle Memorial Fund
- Correspondence, 1913-1952; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains files arranged in alphabetical order by name of correspondent.
  - A-Br (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Br-Da (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Da-Em (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Department of the Interior, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of the Interior, 1916-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - F-He (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - He-L (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hovey, Edmund Otis (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Howe, Ernest (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - M-O (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - P-R (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sa-Sm (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sm-We (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - We-Wr (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Topical files, 1923-1945; Series II
  This series contains files arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Bristol Public School diploma, 1909 June 25 (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - Catalogue of Personal Library: Volume 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Catalogue of Personal Library; Volume 2 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Council of the American Geographical Society certificate of membership, 1917 January 23 (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - Davenport College Directory, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Descriptions of Specimens
    - "Cyclopidius", Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Desmatochoerus", Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Geological Horizons", Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "Leptauchenia", Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Merychyus", Undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "Merycochoerus", Undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "Merycoides", Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - "Metoreodon", Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Oreodontoides", Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "Paroreodon", Undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "Phenacocelus", Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Poatrephes", Undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - "Promerycochoerus", Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - "Pronomotherium", Undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - "Tichololeptus", Undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Dissertation (Ph.D.) (Box 5, Folder 33-38)
  - Lecture notes (Box 6, Folder 39-40)
  - Lists (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Environment and Racial Character" by Huntington, E., 1923 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - "North Branford Fossils", 1929 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - "A Remarkable Woodchuck Skull", 1929 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - "Story about Portheus molossus ", 1934 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - "Additional Notes on Oreodontoides oregonensis Thorpe", Undated (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - "Araeocyon, a Probable Old World Migrant", Undated (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - "The Generic Distinctions between Merycochoerus Leidy and Promerycochoerus Douglass", Undated (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - "How to Macerate Skeleton", Undated (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - "The Hyoid Apparatus of Merycoidodon", Undated (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - "John Day Eporeodons, with Descriptions...", Undated (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - "Leptauchenia Leidy and Cyclopidius (Pithecistestes) Cope..., Undated (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - "A New Genus of Oligocene Hyaenodontidae", Undated (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - "New Reconstructions at the Peabody Museum", Undated (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - "A New Species of Extinct Peccary from Oregon", Undated (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - "New Species of Uinta Carnivora", Undated (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - "Notes on the Bridger (Eocene) Carnivora", Undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - "On Measurements for the Oligocene Felidae", Undated (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - "Oregon Tertiary Canidae...", Undated (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - "The Osteology of Eporedon socialis Marsh ", Undated (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - "The Primitive, and Carnivorelike Characters of the Merycoidodontidal", Undated (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - "Restoration of Eporedus socialis Marsh", Undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - "The Skeleton of Brontosaurus excelsus Marsh", Undated (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - "Some Tertiary Carnivora in the Marsh Collection", Undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - "Structural Features of the Abajo Mountains", Undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - "Two New Forms of Agriochoerus", Undated (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - "Two New Fossil Carnivora", Undated (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - "White River (Oligocene) Eporeodus", Undated (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - "Wyoming Eocene Fishes", Undated (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Miscellanea, Undated (Box 7, Folder 70-71)
  - Memoirs of the Peabody Museum
    - "Merycoidodentidae", 1936 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - "Bathygenys", Undated (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - "Chelonocephalus", Undated (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - "Cyclopidius", Undated (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - "Eporeodon", Undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - "Eucrotophus", Undated (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - "Geographical Distribution", Undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - "Hymeryx", Undated (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - "Leptauchenia", Undated (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - "Limnenetes", Undated (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - "Merychyus", Undated (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - "Merycochoerus", Undated (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - "Merycoides", Undated (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - "Merycoidodon", Undated (Box 8, Folder 85-86)
    - "Mesoreodon", Undated (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - "Metoreodon", Undated (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - "Oreodontoides", Undated (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - "Oreonetes", Undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - "Paroreodon", Undated (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - "Phenacocoelus", Undated (Box 9, Folder 92)
    - "Plates", Undated (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - "Poatrephes", Undated (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - "Promerycochoerus", Undated (Box 9, Folder 95-96)
    - "Protoreodon", Undated (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - "Ticholeptus", Undated (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Notes and Outline, Undated (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - 1924
    - "Contents, Illustrations, Introduction" (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - "Chapter 1" (Box 10, Folder 101)
    - "Chapter 2" (Box 10, Folder 102)
    - "Chapter 3" (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - "Chapter 4" (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - "Chapter 5" (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - "Chapter 6" (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - "Chapter 7" (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - "Chapter 8" (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Paleontological Charts, Undated (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Personal and Financial Papers, Undated (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Resumé, Undated (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Sigma Xi Society, Undated (Box 10, Folder 112)
    - Oversize, 1920 March 4 (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - Society of Vertebrate Paleontology, Undated (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Student Papers, Undated (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - H. Emerson Tuttle Papers, Undated (Box 11, Folder 115-116)
  - Yale University Commencement, 1934-1936 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Yale University Faculty List, 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Yale University Paleontological Club, Undated (Box 11, Folder 119)